Register of the Sergei Aleksandrovich Semeka Diaries, 1941-1944
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergei Aleksandrovich Semeka diaries
1941-1944
2010C34
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 Linear feet)
The collection contains Semeka's diaries relating to administration of medical services in the Soviet army during World War II.
Semeka, Sergei Aleksandrovich, 1906-1966
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Sergei Aleksandrovich Semeka was born in 1906 in St. Petersburg, Russia. After graduating from the Military Medical Academy in Leningrad, he served the rest of his life in the Soviet Army. Initially appointed as a regimental junior doctor, he rose to become the head of the Military Medical Administration during World War II. Specializing in the organization of medical services for the military in combat, he became one of the youngest generals in the military medical services in 1943, serving as the deputy director in the Department of Military Medicine of the Ministry of Defense of the USSR.
After the war Semeka served as chairman of the Department of Military Medicine in several educational institutions and conducted extensive research in the history of Russian military medicine in the 17th and 18th centuries. Semeka died in 1966.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of Sergei Aleksandrovich Semeka's handwritten World War II diaries detailing his everyday activities organizing frontline medical service for the Soviet Army. The ten notebooks include photographs, clippings, diagrams, plans, and maps reflecting the medical conditions on the Eastern Front.
World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Eastern Front; World War, 1939-1945--Medical care; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union
- Diaries, 1941-1944 (Box 1-2)
  Includes 10 hand-written volumes recording events on the Eastern Front during World War II. Diaries numbered 2, 3, 4, and 6 were not received. Arranged chronologically.
  - # 1, 1941 August 22 - October 12 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - # 5, 1942 May 15 - September 9 (Box-folder 1 :2)
  - # 7, 1942 May 12 - 1943 January 15 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - # 8, 1943 January 16 - April 23 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - # 9, 1943 April 23 - July 28 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - # 10, 1943 July 20 - September 29 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - # 11, 1943 September 30 - October 31 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - # 12, 1943 October 31 - 1944 January 1 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - # 13, 1944 January 2 - March 9 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - # 14, 1944 March 14 - May 18 (Box-folder 2: 5)